Guide to the James William Fesler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional Material, 1925-1991; Accession 1992-M-081; 1; (1 box)
  - Publication and Papers, 1987-1991
    - 5. "Introduction," remarks opening the 2-day program on "The Campus and the Public Service," National Academy of Public Administration, November 19, 1987 (typescript). (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 6. "The State and Its Study: The Whole and the Parts: The Third Annual John Gaus Lecture," PS: Political Science and Politics 21 (Fall 1988), pp. 891-901. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      —Also in Naomi B. Lynn and Aaron Wildaysky (eds.), Public Administration: The State of the Discipline (Chatham, N.J.: Chatham House Publishers, 1990), pp. 84-96. (Volume in Social Science Library: JF1351. P8185X. 1990.)
    - 7. "A Curious Life: The Pursuit of an Understanding of Public Administration," (Berkeley: Institute of Governmental Studies, University of California, 1990) (processed). (Box 1, Folder 14)
      —and excerpt, "Managing Misfits and Organizing the Unorganizable: James Fesler Recalls a Curious Life in Public Administration," Public Affairs Report [Institute of Governmental Studies] 32 (January 1991), pp. 8-9.
    - 8. (with Donald F. Kettl) The Politics of the Administrative Process (Chatham, N.J.: Chatham House Publishers, 1991). (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Volume in Social Science Library: [illegible]
  - Book Reviews
    - Robert Luce, "Legislative Problems," in North Carolina Law Review 14 (February 1936), pp. 208-210. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Finla G. Crawford, "Our Government Today," in Social Forces 14 (May 1936), pp- 617-618. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Selden C. Menafee, "A Plan for Regional Administrative Districts in the State of Washington," American Political Science Review 30 (June 1936), p. 599. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - James K. Coleman, "State Administration in South Carolina," Social Forces 15 (March 1937), pp. 446-448. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Joseph P. Chamberlain, "Legislative Processes: National and State," North Carolina Law Review 15 (April 1937), pp. 304-307. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - American Society of Planning Officials, "New Horizons in Planning," American Political Science Review 32 (April 1938), p. 398-399. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Clarence Lewis Hodge, "The Tennessee Valley Authority," American Political Science Review 33 (April 1939), pp. 311-312. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Edward S. Corwin, "Court Over Constitution," in Journal of Politics 1 (May 1939), pp. 222-223. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - J. Kerwin Wiliams, "Grants-in-Aid Under the Public Works Administration," in American Political Science Review 33 (December 1939), p. 1089. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - George Soule, "An Economic Constitution for Democracy," in North Carolina Law Review 18 (February 1940), pp. 180-181. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Donald C. Blaisdell, "Government and Agriculture," in American Political Science Review 33 (April 1941), p. 375. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - David Bicknell Truman, "Administrative Decentralization: A Study of the Chicago Field Offices of the United States Department of Agriculture," in Southern Economic Journal 8 (July 1941), pp. 126-127. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Paul Studenski and Paul R. Mort, "Centralized vs. Decentralized Government in Relation to Democracy" in Southern Economic Journal 8 (July 1941), pp. 127-128. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Gilbert Gillespie Lentz, "The Enforcement of the Orders of State Public Service Commissions," in Journal of Politics 3 (August 1941), pp. 383-384. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Charles C. Rohlfing, Edward W. Carter, Bradford W. West, and John G. Hervey, "Business and Government," in University of Pennsylvania Law Review 90 (Novembver 1941), pp. 124-126. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - C. Herman Pritchett, "The Tennessee Valley Authority: A Study in Public Administration," in Southern Economic Journal 11 (October 1944), pp. 195ff. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Comstock Glaser, "Administrative Procedure: A Practical Handbook for the Administrative Analyst," in Southern Economic Journal 9 (October 1942), pp. 175ff. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - John Lord O'Brian arid Manly Fleischman, "The War Production Board Administrative Policies and Procedures," in Public Administration Review 5 (Summer 1945), pp. 257-262. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Herbert A. Simon, "Administrative Behavior: A Study of Decision-Making Processes in Administrative Organization," in Journal of Politics 10 (February 1948), pp. 187-189. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Emmette S. Redford, "Field Administration of Wartime Rationing," in Southwestern Social Science Quarterly 28 (March 1948), pp. 375ff. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - George Warren (ed.), "The Federal Administrative Act and the Administrative Agencies," in North Carolina Law Review 26 (April 1948), pp. 326-328. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Dwight Waldo, "The Administrative State: A Study of the Political Theory of American Public Administration," in Amerian Political Science Review 42 (August 1948), pp. 782-783. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Luther Gulick, "Administrative Reflections from World War II," in Journal of Politics 10 (November 1948), pp. 835-837. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - W. K. Hancock and M. M. Gowing, "British War Economy," in American Political Science Review 44 (June 1950), pp. 464-468. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Robert H. Connery, "The Navy and Industrial Mobilization in World War II," in Political Science Quarterly 66 (November 1952), pp. 621-622. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Harold Stein (ed.), "Public Administration and Policy Developoment: A Case Book," in Yale Law Journal 61 (November 1952), pp. 1238-1241. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Advisory Commission on Graduate Education and Research in Government in the South, "Graduate Education and Research in Government in the South," in American Political Science Review 49 (September 1955), p. 915. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - George Albert Smith, Jr., "Managing Geographically Decentralized Companies," in Administrative Science Quarterly 3 (March 1959), pp. 535-537. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Emmette S. Redford, "Ideal and Practice in Public Administration." American Political Science Review 53 (March 1959), pp. 199-200. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - G. E. Aylmer, "The King's Servants: The Civil Service of Charles I, 1625-1642," in Administrative Science Quarterly 7 (June 1962), pp. 125-128. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - W. Lloyd Warner, Paul P. Van Riper, Norman H., Martin, and Orvis F. Collins, "The American Federal Executive," in American Political Science Review 58 (December 1964), pp. 1009-1011. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Michel Crozier, "The Bureaucratic Phenomenon," in Administrative Science Quarterly 10 (September 1965), pp. 261-266. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Daniel J. Elazar, "American Federalism: A View from the States," in American Political Science Review 61 (September 1967), pp. 805-806. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Gerald D. Nash, "Perspectives on Administration: The Vistas of History," in Administrative Science Quarterly 15 (September 1970), pp. 391-392. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Frederick C. Mosher, "The GAO: The Quest for Accountability;" and Erasmus H. Kloman (ed.), "Cases in Accountability: The Work of the GAO," in Political Science Quarterly 95 (Spring 1980), pp. 156-158. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Robert W. Hartman and Arnold R. Weber, "The Rewards of Public Service: Compensating Top Federal Officials," in Political Science Quarterly 95 (Winter 1980-1981), pp. 703-704. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Alberto Guerreiro Ramos, "The New Science of Organizations: A Reconceptualization of the Wealth of Nations," in American Political Science Review 76 (September 1982), p. 741. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lawrence B. Mohr, "Explaining Organizational Behavior: The Limits and the Possibilities," in American Political Science Review 77 (June 1983), pp. 558-559 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Trudi C. Miller (ed.), "Public Sector Performance: A Conceptual Turning Point," in Political Science Quarterly 100 (Spring 1985), pp. 170-171. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - David Burner and Thomas R. West, "The Torch Is Passed: The Kennedy Brothers and American Liberalism," in Presidential Studies Quarterly 15 (Summer 1985), pp. 634-636. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Book Reviews by JWF
    - Ben W. Heineman, Jr., and Curtis A. Hessler, "Memorandum for the President: A Strategic Approach to Domestic Affairs in the 1980s;" and Fred L. Israel (gen. ed.), "Major Presidential Decisions," in Presidential Studies Quarterly 16 (Spring 1986), pp. 373-375. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Peri E. Arnold, "Making the Managerial Presidency: Comprehensive Reorganization Planning, 1905-1980," in Political Science Quarterly 101 (No. 3, 1986). pp. 507-509. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Richard W. Waterman, "Presidential Influence and the Administrative State," in American Political Science Review 84 (September 1990), p 1021. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Herbert Simon, "Models of My Life," in Public Administration Review 52 (March/April 1992), pp. 210-211. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Honors
    - Fellow, National Academy of Public Administration, 1968- (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Fellow, American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1968- (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Dwight Waldo Award "for distinguished contributions to the professional literature of public administration," American Society for Public Administration, (April 1986) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bosworth Memorial Award "for sustained contribution to the field of public administration," Connecticut Chapter of the American Society for Public Administration, (September 1986) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - John Gaus Award, American Political Science Association, "to honor a lifetime of exemplary scholarship in the joint tradition of political science and public administration", (September 1988) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Fellow, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1991- (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Teaching Acknowledgments
    - Aaron Wildavsky, "Things I Never Knew," in The Revolt Against the Masses (New York: Basic Books, 1971), pp. vii-xi, at viii. Essay reprinted in Wildavsky, Craftways: On the Organization of Scholarly Work (New Brunswick, NJ: Transaction Publishers, 1989), pp. 147-152, at 148-149. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      The Craftways excerpt is included in the folder.
    - Robert T. Golembiewski and Aaron Wildavsky (eds.), The Costs of Federalism: Essays in Honor of James W. Fesler (New Brunswick, N.J.: Transaction Books, 1984). (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Volume in Social Science Library: JK325. C629. 1984.
  - Book Dedications
    - William L. Bacchus, Foreign Policy and the Bureaucratic Process (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1974). (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Douglas Yates, The Ungovernable City: The Politics of Urban Problems and Policy Making (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1977). (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Donald F. Kettl, Leadership at the Fed (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1986). (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Programs, 1925-1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Income tax/expenses, 1941-1987 (Box 1, Folder 18-21)
- Additional Material, 1988-1989; Accession 1992-M-082; 0.25; (1 box)
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1993 Feb
  Received from: Transferred from the Social Science Library, 1992 Jun. Given to the library by James W. Fesler, 1991 May.
  - Leadership for America: Rebuilding the Public Service: drafts of the Task Force reports of the National Commission on the Public Service, Paul A. Volcker, chairman, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1950-1991 (inclusive), 1979-1991 (bulk); Accession 1996-M-088
  - Correspondence
    - 1950-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - A-K, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2-12)
    - Kaufman, Herbert, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - L-P, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14-19)
    - Q-Z, 1979-1991 (Box 2, Folder 20-26)
  - Course syllabi, 1969-1979 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Yale University Press
    - Marian Neal Ash/Social Science (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Publications Committee
      - 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - 1979 October 15-1980 June 16 (Box 3, Folder 30-38)
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-078
  - Slides of trip to Africa [possibly for conferences, index included], 1952-mid 1950s (Box 1)